[Music]
hello and very warm welcome to all of
you on this special episode of world
heart day i see i say lombard presents
they'll say partnered by et now now
heart attack and stroke are words that
are not unknown anymore the number of
people suffering from cardiovascular
diseases has been rapidly increasing
over the past few years with an
estimated 54.5 million in india alone
suffering from it globally 520 million
people are living with cardiovascular
diseases and kovitt 19 has further added
to their woes because many have been
afraid to attend routine and emergency
appointments because they are worried
and they are scared that they would
contract the virus
this has in turn also led people to
become isolated from friends and
families now this healthcare crisis has
made it urgent to find different and
innovative ways to connect people to
heart health particularly among the
lower resource population
and on this world heart day september
29th times network along with icici
lombard is trying to find out the causes
that make one prone to cardiac ailments
over the years the role of health
insurance in protection and rebuilding
the heart and what we can do to protect
ourselves and to save our hearts
we have two special experts joining us
on this panel allow me to introduce them
we have mr bhargavdas gupta he's the md
at icici lombard general insurance and
we also have padma bhushan and
padmashree awardee dr ashok said the
chairman at fortis escorts heart
institute gentlemen thank you so much
for joining me here today dr said i'd
like to start with you
first up so um despite the increasing
awareness around heart health number of
cardiovascular diseases people suffering
from cardiovascular diseases is
increasing at an alarming rate globally
as well as in india how can one be more
aware and vigilant for early signs and
to prevent a serious situation you're so
right sumit uh
india has become the heart attack
capital of the world uh to tell you
frankly deaths from heart disease in the
west have decreased by 50 percent
decreased by 50 in the last 30 years
deaths from heart disease in india have
increased 300 percent
in the last 30 years
three times the incidence of coronary
arteries and as a race we've got to
understand
that we're more prone to have heart
disease uh we are three times more prone
than europeans for the same risk factors
rather for similar risk factors three
times more prone to europeans
six times
more prone than chinese and 20 times
more than japanese to have partisans
so as as so we practically as a race we
are loaded guns
who could actually develop heart disease
if the circumstances became
unfavorable to each of us and that's why
both for men
and women heart disease has become the
biggest killer
it used to be 10 years ago infections
but now it's the heart disease for both
men and women so yes and the reason
one of the other big concerns i must
point out is that over the last 15 years
heart disease in young individuals which
means people less than 50
has actually increased 200 percent
and that's the last 15 years
so these are worrying
worrying statistics
especially when we think that 50 of our
population is youth
and if they're getting affected by heart
disease at an early age what's going to
happen in 10 years and 15 years 20 years
and of course we can discuss why this
has happened
but we have to face the reality and
that's why
this program the messaging to people
how to prevent heart disease how to
control it has become equally important
absolutely and doctor said i will come
back to you on those important points
because it's like almost like we're
sitting on a ticking bomb in this sense
i will come back to you on that in a
second i just want to go over to uh mr
das gupta so you know
in my intro i said this that it is that
the pandemic has an imp had has had an
impact on everyone across the globe but
how has it impacted the health insurance
industry specifically well sumit you're
right this is something that uh
obviously has affected the whole world
and when you look at insurance uh
insurance model really works in a
situation where a lot of people
contribute small amounts to create our
insurance pool and a few people have an
accident or a damage or a health event
and a large amount is paid out for each
one of them that's how the insurance
model works so when there's a pandemic
that becomes a real challenge for the
industry now if you look at what's uh
happened for our industry uh given the
wave one and the wave two that we've
just recently seen
the industry has taken a hit of uh
already more than 30 000 crores
this was never expected or priced into
our product so that's been one immediate
uh adverse impact that we've had as an
industry and by the way as an industry
unlike most industries that got affected
we've not gone back to anyone uh asking
for
you know any any support from the
government or anyone else so that's one
negative the at the same time uh you
know in one way it has increased the
awareness of health insurance and if you
look at the
the the research that people are doing
about health care and health insurance
that's seen a significant jump and if
you see mercy consequently the demand
for health insurance has uh increased
very rapidly if you look at the last
you know 89 months healthy insurance has
grown at about 35 percent uh in terms of
the premium collection so while the
first is a huge negative from a short
term perspective the second is in the
long term what potentially are positive
the third thing that has happened that
we are observing is that people are
realizing the importance of buying
proper cover in the past people would
buy a three
and laptop and i think this is probably
the most important uh change that we are
seeing
is the uh the health seeking behavior
for customers are changing
and people are getting more comfortable
with digital health
tele health you know virtual doctors and
seeking those services beyond just you
know hospitalization when some big
episode happens so we are seeing
multiple changes uh you know in the
whole paradigm of health insurance
you know largely driven by inspection
doctor said you know for an average
adult how much of exercise or physical
activity is sufficient to keep
cardiovascular disease at bay because
you know sedentary lifestyle is said to
be one of the major causes of heart
attacks your thoughts on that exercise
is one area which actually controls a
lot of things within your body for
example if i told you
that 45 minutes of exercise with a five
minute warm-up and a five-minute
cooldown
five times a week
decreases our chances of heart attack by
that's huge because it controls our
weight
it actually people who actually
exercise their blood pressure comes
under control if they have diabetes that
comes under control it actually gives a
cells of well-being people who are you
know wanting to be fit give up smoking
they actually want to exercise better
and it gives a sense of positivity so it
actually takes care of all the factors
including stress exercise takes care of
that as well
and so importantly is this fact that it
cannot be compared
to jimmy
yes if gemming in ward on the treadmill
aerobic exercises aerobic exercises are
great for the heart
but yes the youth today wants to go to
gyms to build up muscles to build up
fadi look good which there's nothing
wrong with that
but the
the the important aspect to realize is
that is not necessarily heart health
heart health revolves around aerobic
exercises getting the heart rate to a
particular level and then going down and
gibbing is a is for physical fitness of
muscle building for perhaps running 10
kilometers is not necessarily great for
the heart it may be good for stamina it
may be good for weight loss but may not
necessarily be any better for the heart
doctor said i just want to take this one
step ahead you were mentioning this also
but about the diet so
any suggestions that you have about
maintaining a healthy heart diet so that
you know we're eating right and keeping
our heart healthy through nutrition
through right
those who have high blood pressure
diabetes
of course they need to be careful about
their carbohydrates and take maintain
diabetes under good control and maintain
blood pressure under good control and
take less of saltish food
apart from that i would say
that we into diet fads at the moment
actually the balanced diet the most
nourishing diet is the balance that
without any extremes
where you actually take the evening meal
much earlier than then later so you you
know you finish your meals by seven
eight o'clock
and if they're home cooked meals
which are normally cooked in the usual
oils
the healthy oils then there's nothing to
exclude from the diet the key word is
balance the diet there uh mr
another point that we were talking about
is uh
so
coming back to the impact of the
pandemic now obviously uh for people
health insurance is important otherwise
also the pandemic has made it even more
important
and people are more aware about it now
but i know that your organization one of
the important steps during the pandemic
was to keep communicating with customers
what are some of the initiatives that
were taken by cic lombard to support
customers during the covet 19 pandemic
well sumit you know like everyone else
we were also affected as individuals
right so we had to also go into a
lockdown right in the beginning you know
all of us were warranted
but thankfully over the years we had
invested heavily in terms of our digital
uh infrastructure and that helped us in
this period in terms of communication
so we took a lot of effort in the first
month you know back in april 2020 in
terms of digitally communicating with
our distribution as also our our
customers but very soon thereafter we
realized that there were
certain other features that we needed to
offer
first was that even before the the
regulator asked the industry to uh you
know consider issuing a covet-specific
policy we launched one uh you know
usually in a pandemic environment as i
explained it's very difficult to launch
a health insurance or any insurance
product it's like you know giving
insurance to someone whose house is
burning uh so in a pandemic institution
is something like that but we felt that
it was our responsibility as a company
to launch a covet specific product
thereafter what we did was uh for our
standard products the normal indemnity
hospitalization plans we said uh not
only will we cover over treatment for
hospitalization we also said that
you know the waiting period which is
usually a 30-day waiting period he said
we'll reduce it to 15 days for covet
because again you know it was a it was a
crisis for our customers we said we need
to do that for our customers
third thing that we did for on the
product side was to say that when you
claim on a covet uh incident you know
because it's a pandemic we will not take
away the benefit that you have for no
non claim right so we have a equivalent
of a no claim bonus called additional
sum in short so if you don't claim for a
year then next to their summing should
goes up we said if you have a covert
incident we will not uh you know reduce
the sum in short next year
thereafter what we realized was the
customers were actually seeking
different types of you know service in
the sense that as i said digital health
you know healthcare service
so we said that customers were worried
about going to hospitals at this point
in time for other uh ailments so we
launched a telehealth service we had the
capability but we started giving it out
for our normal customers you know to
teleconsulting free normally it's a
price product for people who buy that
cup but we gave it out to uh to our
customers for free and then we launched
uh you know home based health care again
you know people are
afraid of going to hospitals we said on
a cashless basis we wanted to be
cashless so that we could ensure the
quality of treatment and the fact that
we were aware of the protocol as was as
per you know doctor's protocol so we'll
launch a cashless home health benefit so
there's been multiple initiatives that
we did uh you know very soon after the
uh pandemic hit us on that note it's
time for a very short break here on this
special world heart day show i see i
said lombard presents dilsa partnered by
et now don't go anywhere we'll be right
back
[Music]
welcome back to icici lombard presents
dilsey partnered by et now it's a very
special show that we're doing on the
occasion of world heart day i'm joined
by two speakers mr bhargavas gupta the
md at icici lombard general insurance
and padma bhushan and padmashree
he's the chairman at fortis escorts art
institute doctor said you know in my
opinion and you're the experts who i
would love to hear from you on this it's
really important that laymen everyday
common people should be aware of first
aid skills if someone around them is
having a heart attack all of a sudden
what's the first thing that we should do
because by the time help arrives if
there are some simple things that we can
do it can help people if you could guide
us on that there are certain cities in
the west like seattle where the public
has actually been trained to deal with
such situations and resuscitate people
with actually multiple lives being saved
in the city because every public every
person a majority of the people know how
to resuscitate we call it
cardiopulmonary resuscitation
now it's not too difficult to learn and
many centers have started training and
teaching public around this
but if someone drops and this could
happen in our own family it could happen
to our friends it could happen to even
in a mall as we're walking if somebody
just collapses the first thing
is to lie him down flat
that's the first thing
secondly to understand
whether he's breathing or not breathing
thirdly at the same time he say
call for help right which means call an
ambulance service call a police service
but immediately tell someone to call
that police
the fourth thing we do is make sure his
head is pulled back so that his tongue
doesn't drop in and therefore he's
breathing
give you know many people start giving
water at that time that's a bad thing
because the person may be unconscious
and therefore you may actually put water
and that may go into the lungs so the
main thing is to keep his airways open
so we call it airways open which means
tilt his head backwards so that his
tongue doesn't drop on his airway
the fifth thing is give him a big thump
on the chest
when hearted when when these sudden
heart attacks or arrhythmias occur and
cause sudden collapse a single thumb to
the chest may restore
the rhythm back to normal and so it's a
single thumb to the chest and finally
as you seek help
you make sure you're not lying in the
middle of the road you're actually
somewhere which is safe for you and the
patient your second help actually push
put tills the head back and you just
start compressing the center of the
chest
right here
at a rate of 70 per minute
so that you actually restore as much
circulation to the brain as possible as
long as you continue that crisply you
will be able to maintain a person till
their health arrived for a period of a
few minutes and those few minutes are
the vital ones that you need to maintain
the intervention absolutely thank you so
much for that doctor that is really
really key uh for for for others i just
want you to to tell you that we used to
talk about the mouth-to-mouth
respiration also at the same time it is
not essential what is essential is
keeping the areas open and actually
pressing the chest and of course in
these days of course we also want to
emphasize that it's pressing the chest
which is far more important than the
mouth-to-mouth respirations absolutely
thank you so much for highlighting these
really important points um mr das gupta
you know uh just taking this point ahead
world heart date is here it's a really
important day in the calendar especially
for india and doctor state has also
spoken about what our scenario here is
uh any specific offerings from icici
lombard for world heart day for for
people out here
sumit there are you know multiple things
that we are doing but before i get into
what we're doing i think it's important
to explain the philosophy that we are
building the health insurance model on
i think global research shows that the
entire effort on preventive
for you know normal consumers and
disease management for people at risk
leads to tremendous benefit for the
consumers in terms of lower incidence of
hospitalization i mean there are
research that shows that even for uh you
know high-risk patients if you manage
the preventive and the disease
management well the incident rates drop
by you know 20 to 30 percent
so our entire effort has been to focus
on this entire wellness and the
preventive
side so we have an app uh called i'll
take care lab which focuses on these
aspects along with normal insurance
services uh and this this app was
launched before comet but has really
picked up uh you know in the last 18
months uh today we have more than eight
and a half lakh uh downloads of this app
now here we've kind of focused on some
of these you know wellness and
preventive services uh one of the things
that we've done uh specifically as a as
you know as a launch in this period was
a calorie counter because one of the
things that we've realized is that among
many features of uh you know wellness
and benefit diet plays a very important
role and we've had nutritionists and you
know health coaches etc which were
available but we have added a calorie
counter uh so you can you know scan your
items and you can you know count the
calories
the other thing that we've done is uh
you know multiple types of products so
what i talked about is service we also
looked at products doctor said i want to
talk to you now about the important role
of technology because uh we know that
technology has been a great help during
covert 19 in every sector every industry
especially telemedicine
your thoughts on how we can use this to
cater to regular needs and medical
investigation for cardiovascular
diseases and your opinion where does
india's health care system stand
considering today's technological
advanced world where are we headed to
your thoughts india is perhaps there are
more cell phones
in india
than anywhere else in the world so
that's an important aspect
our prime minister himself is talking
about
even as of today 5g
and and uh wi-fi for all in this country
which is a great step forwards and once
we see that we know that a lot of
monitoring
a lot of real-time help
can be given by remote monitoring there
is also real-time ecg monitoring but
artificial intelligence is coming in
hugely as an interface between the
patient and the doctor to start
immediately advising him look this is
abnormal
we think you should take an extra tablet
by the time your doctor answers you
or for example look at the ecg this is
your real-time ecg we think that this
ecg suddenly changed abnormal
we think you should contact a doctor so
artificial intelligence can even do
a lot of help to the doctor by removing
that lag time between the time
real-time monitoring where the pa where
the patient cannot see the abnormality
but artificial intelligence can see an
abnormality and transfer it to the
patient and give the give the patient an
advice and yet transfer it to the doctor
to to decrease the lag phase fantastic
that's a great uh leap for innovation
which is definitely going to make a big
uh mark and provide a lot of help to
people uh just as we wind up one last
question to mr das gupta so what are
some of the new product launches from
icici lombard that we can expect to see
soon or that have been recently launched
by the organization you're right in the
sense that a heart ailment creates
significant uh you know financial impact
and if you look at the prevalence of
heart disease it's really even you know
between
the young age group of let's say up to
20 to 49 uh one in seven uh people
suffer a you know heart ailment it's a
very high number
and we've launched a critical illness
plan which covers 200 different uh you
know critical illnesses including heart
with a lot of features in terms of
lifetime uh coverage so even multiple
claims uh you know reset benefits
etcetera so so there are multiple
features that we've launched
lastly as i said the entire journey for
us is to provide end-to-end healthcare a
continuum of care starting with
preventive to critical care
so on that we've launched a b fit
product where you can actually get
cashless opt service
all of these features in terms of your
health coach wellness guidance nutrition
etc
plus if you unfortunately need to get
treated there is a you know network of
you know general practitioners uh
pharmacy chains uh diagnostic centers so
in not just hospitalization even for
non-hospitalization you can get those
you know covers uh on our on our app so
these are some of the uh products and
services that we've launched around the
world
world hardly doctor state as we wind up
this episode just wanting your closing
comments any message that you want to
leave our viewers with on the occasion
of world heart day firstly of course
i've always said
that prevention of heart disease
protection from heart attacks
is in your hands and in fact it's not
just in your hands it's actually in your
feet
it doesn't require great investments it
just requires
sports shoes is what you buy and the
roads on which you walk and you decrease
your heart attack so that's the first
thing in fact it takes lesser uh it's
it's least expensive to decrease heart
attacks because you eat healthy you
don't actually eat out you actually give
up smoking and you save money so
everything that you do to prevent heart
disease saves you money and the and the
second aspect i would say is prevention
prevention prevention if you have risk
factors
if anyone or i have risk factors which
means smoking or diabetes or
hypertension
and i have a strong family history where
someone in my family has
had a heart attack at a young age or
passed away suddenly at a young age i
must start my checkups as early as the
age of 20 or 25 and have regular
checkups from the doctors so that
early signs can be picked up initially
and preventive measures put in so that
the same faith which happened to say our
closed near and rear relatives do not
happen to us prevention goes along those
lines regular checkup
and taking your own personal actions
those two are important stay well stay
healthy save your heart that's the most
important absolutely thank you so much
dr said for that that was really
beautifully put
so thank you so much my one message to
everyone would be that our most
cherished asset is our health and this
is something that has come home
very very uh
starkly to all of us in this period so
do take care of yourself do take care of
your health do take care of your heart
well that's all the time that we have
today on this special show i see i said
lombard presents bill say partnered by
et now where we were talking to mr
bhargavdas gupta the md at ici salon by
general insurance and also to padma
bhushan and padmashree awardee dr ashok
sheth the chairman of fortis escorts art
institute on the special occasion of
world heart day thank you so much for
watching stay safe and stay healthy
[Music]